Traditional prescriptions for growth in Africa are not working very well.
لم تعمل الوصفات التقليدية للنمو في أفريقيا بشكل جيد جدًا.
After one trillion dollars in African development-related aid
بعد تريليون دولار من المساعدات من أجل التنمية في أفريقيا
in the last 60 years,
في السنوات ال 60 الماضية،
real per capita income today is lower than it was in the 1970s.
اليوم، نصيب الفرد من الدخل الحقيقي هو أقل مما كان عليه في السبعينات.
Aid is not doing too well.
يبدو أن المساعدات ليست جيدة جدًا.
In response,
وردًا على ذلك،
the Bretton Woods institutions -- the IMF and the World Bank --
فإن مؤسسات بريتون وودز - صندوق النقد الدولي والبنك الدولي -
pushed for free trade not aid,
شجعت التجارة الحرة وليس المساعدات،
yet the historical record shows little empirical evidence
ويبين السجل التاريخي بقليل من الأدلة التجريبية
that free trade leads to economic growth.
أن التجارة الحرة هي التي تؤدي إلى النمو الاقتصادي.
The newly prescribed silver bullet is microcredit.
أما الحل السحري المقرر حديثًا فهو القروض الصغرى.
We seem to be fixated on this romanticized idea
يبدو أننا نركز اهتمامنا على هذه الفكرة الرومانسية
that every poor peasant in Africa is an entrepreneur.
التي جعلت كل الفلاحين الفقراء في أفريقيا رواد أعمال.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yet my work and travel in 40-plus countries across Africa
لقد علمني العمل والسفر في أكثر من 40 بلدًا في جميع أنحاء أفريقيا
have taught me that most people want jobs instead.
أن معظم الناس يريدون وظائف بدلًا من ذلك.
My solution: Forget micro-entrepreneurs.
الحل هو: انسوا أصحاب المشاريع الصغيرة.
Let's invest in building pan-African titans
دعونا نستثمر في بناء عمالقة أفريقيا
like Sudanese businessman Mo Ibrahim.
مثل رجل الأعمال السوداني مو إبراهيم.
Mo took a contrarian bet on Africa when he founded Celtel International in '98
لقد راهن مو على أفريقيا عندما أسس شركة سلتل الدولية في '98
and built it into a mobile cellular provider
وبنى مزودًا للاتصال اللاسلكي
with 24 million subscribers across 14 African countries by 2004.
مع 24 مليون مشترك في 14 بلدًا أفريقيًا بحلول عام 2004.
The Mo model might be better than the everyman entrepreneur model,
قد يكون هذا النموذج لمو أفضل من نماذج كل رواد الأعمال،
which prevents an effective means of diffusion and knowledge-sharing.
الذي يمنع أي وسيلة فعّالة لنشر وتبادل المعرفة.
Perhaps we are not at a stage in Africa
ربما نحن لسنا في مرحلة متقدمة في أفريقيا
where many actors and small enterprises leads to growth through competition.
حيث العديد من المقاولات الصغيرة تسعى إلى النمو من خلال المنافسة.
Consider these two alternative scenarios.
لننظر إلى هذين السيناريوهين البديلين.
One: You loan 200 dollars to each of 500 banana farmers
الأول: تقرض 200 دولار لكل من 500 مزارع للموز
allowing them to dry their surplus bananas
مما يسمح لهم بتجفيف فائضهم من الموز
and fetch 15 percent more revenue at the local market.
وجلب المزيد من العائدات بنسبة 15 في المائة من السوق المحلية.
Or two: You give 100,000 dollars to one savvy entrepreneur
أو الثاني: تعطي 100,000 دولار لرجل أعمال ذكي واحد
and help her set up a factory that yields 40 percent additional income
ونساعده على إنشاء مصنع يدر 40 في المئة من الدخل الإضافي
to all 500 banana farmers and creates 50 additional jobs.
لكل ال500 مزارع ويخلق 50 وظيفة إضافية.
We invested in the second scenario,
لقد استثمرنا في السيناريو الثاني،
and backed 26-year-old Kenyan entrepreneur Eric Muthomi
ودعمنا رجل الأعمال الكيني ذو ال26 عامًا أريك ماتومي
to set up an agro-processing factory called Stawi
لإنشاء مصنع تجهيز المنتجات الزراعية المسمى "Stawi"
to produce gluten-free banana-based flour and baby food.
لإنتاج دقيق الموز وأغذية الأطفال الخالية من الغلوتين.
Stawi is leveraging economies of scale
يستفيد مصنع "Stawi" من اقتصاد الحجم
and using modern manufacturing processes to create value for not only its owners
ويستخدم عمليات التصنيع الحديثة لخلق القيمة ليس فقط لأصحابه
but its workers, who have an ownership in the business.
ولكن أيضًا لعماله، الذين يملكون جزءًا من الشركة.
Our dream is to take an Eric Muthomi and try to help him become a Mo Ibrahim,
حلمنا هو أن نساعد أريك ماتومي ليصبح مو إبراهيم،
which requires skill, financing, local and global partnerships,
الأمر الذي يتطلب مهارةً وتمويلًا وشراكات محلية وعالمية،
and extraordinary perseverance.
ومثابرة استثنائية.
But why pan-African?
ولكن لماذا لعموم أفريقيا؟
The scramble for Africa during the Berlin Conference of 1884 --
التدافع لأفريقيا خلال مؤتمر برلين 1884 -
where, quite frankly, we Africans were not exactly consulted --
حيث، بكل صراحة، نحن الأفارقة لم تتم استشارتنا بالضبط -
(Laughter) (Applause) --
(ضحك) (تصفيق) -
resulted in massive fragmentation
أسفرت عن تجزئة ضخمة
and many sovereign states with small populations:
والعديد من الدول ذات السيادة قليلة السكان:
Liberia, four million; Cape Verde, 500,000.
ليبيريا، أربعة ملايين. والرأس الأخضر، 500,000.
Pan-Africa gives you one billion people,
تعداد سكان أفريقيا مليار شخص،
granted across 55 countries with trade barriers and other impediments,
موزعين على 55 دولة محصورة بحواجز تجارية وغيرها من المعوقات،
but our ancestors traded across the continent
ولكن أجدادنا مارسوا التجارة في جميع أنحاء القارة
before Europeans drew lines around us.
قبل أن يرسم الأوروبيين خطوطًا حولنا.
The pan-African opportunities outweigh the challenges,
فرص الأفريقي تفوق التحديات،
and that's why we're expanding Stawi's markets from just Kenya
وهذا هو السبب وراء توسيع أسواق "Stawi" من مجرد كينيا
to Algeria, Nigeria, Ghana, and anywhere else that will buy our food.
إلى الجزائر، ونيجيريا، وغانا، وأي مكان آخر يمكن أن يشتري طعامنا.
We hope to help solve food security, empower farmers, create jobs,
نأمل المساعدة في حل مشكلة الأمن الغذائي ودعم المزارعين وخلق فرص عمل
develop the local economy, and we hope to become rich in the process.
وتطوير الاقتصاد المحلي، ونأمل أن نصبح أغنياء في هذه العملية.
While it's not the sexiest approach,
في حين أنها ليست أحسن طريقة،
and maybe it doesn't achieve the same feel-good
وربما لا تحقق نفس الإحساس الجيد
as giving a woman 100 dollars to buy a goat on kiva.org,
كما أنه بمنحنا 100 دولار لامرأة لشراء الماعز على kiva.org،
perhaps supporting fewer, higher-impact entrepreneurs
ربما ندعم أصحاب المشاريع ذات التأثير العالي
to build massive businesses that scale pan-Africa
لبناء شركات ضخمة قادرة على الدفع بأفريقيا
can help change this.
يمكن أن تساعد في تغيير هذا الوضع.
The political freedom for which our forebearers fought
الحرية السياسية التي من أجلها حارب أسلافنا
is meaningless without economic freedom.
لا معنى لها من دون الحرية الاقتصادية.
We hope to aid this fight for economic freedom
نأمل المساعدة في هذه المعركة من أجل الحرية الاقتصادية
by building world-class businesses,
من خلال بناء شركات عالمية،
creating indigenous wealth,
قادرة على خلق الثروة الأصلية،
providing jobs that we so desperately need,
وتوفير فرص العمل التي نحن في أمس الحاجة إليها،
and hopefully helping achieve this.
ونأمل أن نساعد على تحقيق ذلك.
Africa shall rise.
أفريقيا يجب أن تعلو.
Thank you.
شكرًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Tom Rielly: So Sangu, of course, this is strong rhetoric.
توم رايلي: سانغو، بالطبع، هذا خطاب قوي.
You're making 100 percent contrast between microcredit
إنك تقر بوجود اختلاف كبير بين القروض الصغرى
and regular investment and growing regular investment.
والاستثمار المنتظم والاستثمار المنتظم المتزايد.
Do you think there is a role for microcredit at all?
هل تعتقد أنه لا يوجد دور للقروض الصغرى على الإطلاق؟
Sangu Delle: I think there is a role.
سانغو ديلي: أعتقد أن هناك دور.
Microcredit has been a great, innovative way
كانت القروض الصغرى جيدة، وطريقة مبتكرة
to expand financial access to the bottom of the pyramid.
لتوسيع الاستفادة من التمويل لصالح أسفل الهرم.
But for the problems we face in Africa,
ولكن بالنسبة للمشاكل التي نواجهها في أفريقيا،
when we are looking at the Marshall Plan
عندما ننظر إلى خطة مارشال
to revitalize war-torn Europe,
لإنعاش أوروبا التي مزقتها الحرب،
it was not full of donations of sheep.
لم تكن مجرد تبرعات بالغنم.
We need more than just microcredit.
نحن بحاجة إلى أكثر من مجرد قروض صغرى.
We need more than just give 200 dollars.
نحن بحاجة إلى أكثر من مجرد إعطاء 200 دولار.
We need to build big businesses, and we need jobs.
نحن بحاجة إلى بناء شركات كبيرة، ونحن بحاجة لفرص العمل.
TR: Very good. Thank you so much.
توم رايلي: جيد جدًا. شكرًا جزيلًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)